Chinese political culture is strange, to say the
least. China has made unbelievably fast progress
in almost every area of society in the past
couple decades, by basically every observable
metric. But, that isn’t to say everyone in
China is perfectly content with the country,
or that other more abstract problems haven’t
appeared in recent times. Political repression
and economic stagnation for the middle
class have led to discontent and a
nostalgia for China’s recent past.
China’s advances have come at the cost of
increased government oversight and meddling in the
lives of its citizens, leading many to yearn for
times of comparative freedom, even if people were
poorer and the country was less developed during
those times. One leader has come to embody and
symbolize this spirit, that being Jiang Zemin.
Jiang was a fascinating and unique person, both
in his life and his political career.
Before we get into it, I’ll mention that sources
about Jiang Zemin tend to be pretty biased,
either for or against him. There isn’t a lot of
neutral discussion like there is about someone
like Deng Xiaoping or Hua Guofeng. Doesn’t
help that he was a decently controversial
guy who only died recently. I’ve pulled from a
lot of different sources, and tried to follow
the most cohesive and even-keeled narrative,
and stick to the facts as best I can.
Jiang Zemin was born on August 17th,
1926, in Yangzhou, in eastern China,
to a large, generally well off family. From
a young age, he enjoyed reading and poetry,
and became a fan of French and Russian literature.
His family wasn’t very political, and he developed
his early communist sympathies as part of student
movements in Yangzhou. Part of what spurred
his early political beliefs were the Japanese
incursions into China throughout the 1930s.
Chiang Kai-shek, the military dictator of
China, saw the communist movement in the
country as a bigger threat than the literal
empire encroaching on his country. Famously,
he said, “The Japanese are a disease of the skin,
the Communists are a disease of the heart.” A
few army officers arrested him in late 1936, and
demanded he seek an alliance with the communists,
which he eventually did. The most notable
officer was the general Zhang Xueliang, who
Jiang Zemin praised for this in an essay he wrote
for a high school entrance exam in 1937.
Also in 1937, Yangzhou fell to the Japanese.
Yangzhou was spared much of the brutality
characteristic of Japanese occupation, but Jiang
and his family were still affected. He had to
quit school, and many men in his family had been
conscripted earlier and were away at war. School
resumed in late 1939, now with the Japanese
language as a required class. He apparently
hated this class, which is a little strange
for someone who would later learn at least
five languages. Jiang later stated his Japanese
would have been better if he wasn’t forced to
learn it under a military occupation.
He attended college in Nanjing in 1943, later
transferring to a school in Shanghai, all still
under Japanese occupation. Throughout his college
years, he participated in many pro-communist
protests, against both the Japanese, and later,
the Nationalist government. He graduated in 1947
with a degree in electrical engineering. Jiang
worked in various factories around Shanghai
through the end of the ‘40s and early ‘50s,
everything from an ice cream factory to a soap
making plant. After the People’s Liberation Army
gained control of the city in the midst of the
civil war, he also joined formally joined the
communist party. He was made party secretary
for various industries and factories throughout
the Shanghai area, dealing with communicating
between the government and the factories.
In 1953, China set out to build their first
automotive factory, in Changchun, with Soviet
help. In 1954, Jiang was sent to Changchun to help
with the construction efforts. He was selected
to be one of seven hundred technicians sent to
the Soviet Union to learn from an existing car
factory in Moscow. He was enrolled in a language
school in Changchun, where he quickly learned
Russian. He spent most of 1955 and ‘56 in Moscow,
learning how to run a car plant. He returned to
the Changchun plant in 1957, just in time for
the first trucks to come off the line.
He worked at the factory for five years, until
he could leverage a political connection, Wang
Daohan, a friend from college, to get a job
back in Shanghai, as director of an electronics
research institute. One of his main objectives
was to find international partners to help
develop China’s domestic electronics industry.
As part of this, he was sent to Japan, via Hong
Kong. He was very impressed with both of these
places, and hoped to apply the principles that
made them successful back home in China.
He continued managing the research institute,
generally unaffected by the chaos and upheaval
of the Cultural Revolution and the ‘60s in
China. Jiang got through it better than many,
but he still had quite the ordeal during these
years. For his interest in foreign languages
and literature, he was accused of being a
supporter of foreigners, and wanting to betray
China. His ties with the Soviet Union didn’t
help either, since Sino-Soviet relations had
completely collapsed by this point.
Jiang was sent to a special school for
political correction. The curriculum
consisted of a year of intensive labor on
a farm. He raised pigs and harvested wheat,
eventually clearing all charges against him.
He was deemed “rehabilitated” in 1970, and got
a job in Beijing, working for the foreign affairs
section of the Ministry of the Machine Industries,
his first serious government position.
China had a pretty short friends list in the
early ‘70s, one of which was Romania,
which was trying to distance themselves
from the Soviet Union. To this end, they sent
a request to China for technical assistance in
constructing fifteen machinery factories. Jiang
Zemin was selected to lead the Chinese delegation,
and went through a course to learn Romanian. He
spent two years in Romania, advising the Romanians
on the construction and operations of their
factories. He later said he enjoyed the trip,
and found Romania to be a welcoming place.
Jiang’s next major job was as part of a working
group to restore order in Shanghai in the
chaotic aftermath of Mao’s death in 1976.
Jiang’s task was to repair and strengthen
transportation and industry in the Shanghai
area. His job mostly became firing people
who had jobs they weren’t qualified for,
that were making things inefficient. He kept
this managerial job until 1979, when China
made a major policy shift in establishing
Special Economic Zones, or SEZs.
This policy allowed for the promotion of many
technically minded and politically savvy people,
including Jiang, who was made vice minister of
the whole SEZ project. He was also elected to the
People’s Political Consultative Conference,
a governmental body in China that oversees
many aspects of society that are outside the
direct purview of the Communist Party.
Jiang’s task with the SEZs was to create economic
growth, while maintaining social stability and
party control in the zones. The main source of
economic growth would be foreign investment, and
in 1980, Jiang headed a delegation that visited
twelve countries in Asia, Europe, and North
America. The trip was mostly unsuccessful, with
no foreign countries or companies committing to
anything. Jiang was still inspired by what he saw,
and remarked that Singapore and Ireland’s free
trade models could be applied to the SEZs.
SEZs were still fairly unpopular at the highest
levels of government, but he was able
to narrowly secure support for the idea
with a presentation he gave in front of the
National People’s Congress. The presentation
was described as “logical” and “humorous,”
leading Deng Xiaoping, the new leader of China,
to vocalize his support for Jiang. Jiang was given
conditional approval to go ahead with his plans,
and he was allowed to draft policy for the Xiamen
Special Economic Zone, now making him one of the
most important lawmakers in China.
This job didn’t last, and he lost it when
the economic ministries of China were reorganized
and consolidated in 1982. Thankfully for him, the
government created the Ministry of the Electronics
Industry shortly after, and he was made party
secretary of the ministry after an interview with
the premier of China, Zhao Ziyang. He was promoted
to full minister just a short time later. He
learned this while he was visiting America,
via a friend, hurriedly leaving a dinner party to
call the embassy to confirm his promotion.
This was during his 1983 visit to the US, where he
met with various electronics and computer company
executives, visited universities, and politicians.
He even met with President Reagan briefly,
where they exchanged jokes. Jiang reportedly asked
Reagan why the US won’t export many electronics
and computers to China, to which Reagan responded
that they were worried about them being used for
military purposes. Jiang followed up by asking
why the US was fine with exporting wheat to China,
after all, China feeds their soldiers with it.
Reagan reportedly laughed at this joke.
After returning to China, he faced a difficult
challenge managing an electronics industry that
was more than ten years behind in most aspects.
He somewhat successfully reorganized the industry,
closing inefficient factories, modernizing
the remaining ones, and integrating research
better with the manufacturing. After his
visit to America, he knew how important
computers would become, and helped create some
of China’s first software development teams.
His efforts led to an eightfold increase
in China’s electronics production.
Jiang worked to cultivate a good image of the
reformed electronics industry, and maybe more
importantly, a good image of himself. In one case,
he visited Chen Yun, a respected elder statesman,
with a printed circuit board and a microprocessor,
using a microscope to show him the intricacies of
their designs. The visit was reported on by the
People’s Daily, who highlighted it as an example
of how foreign advancements and tech didn’t have
to clash with the country’s domestic politics and
goals. This was great for Jiang, a Western-minded
politician who seemed to find more value outside
the country than in it, he would have to
constantly buoy his domestic reputation.
Jiang did well in his position as minister of
electronics, but the incessant power struggles
and bureaucracy common in Chinese politics was
beginning to wear on him, and he was looking for
a more low-key assignment. Wang Daohan,
his old political connection and friend,
was mayor of Shanghai, and wasn’t doing a great
job. Shanghai was only growing at about half
the rate of the rest of the country’s economy,
pretty bad for what is generally considered the
financial capitol of the country. Zhao Ziyang
and Jiang Zemin visited Shanghai to talk with
Wang Daohan about potentially replacing him.
Wang Daohan wasn’t happy with his job either,
and an agreement was reached to replace
him with Jiang in the near future.
Jiang started his term as mayor with a press
conference, taking questions from reporters,
instead of the traditional speech. He stated
that Shanghai’s modernization would be based
around three “pillars,” infrastructure, foreign
investment, and technology. Jiang was known at
this time for his frequent casual visits to
many areas of the city. He was known to stop
random people on the street for their opinions
on various problems in the city, he even helped
with work at the dockyards occasionally.
He implemented various free market reforms,
as China was doing as a whole at the time,
which led to some social instability. Prices
had stayed basically the same for thirty
years, and now they had increased by at
least twenty percent for most items. This led
to some minor protests, nothing too crazy,
and Jiang was able to talk them down easily,
but it was a sign of things to come.
Jiang was successful in raising funds from
international investors for improving the city,
securing over three billion dollars. Projects
funded with the money included expanding the
airport, metro system, and water infrastructure,
as well as importing food from other regions to
stabilize food prices. He even got to meet
the queen when she visited Shanghai in 1986,
with Jiang personally overseeing her itinerary
and organizing various events.
Jiang met a lot of people as mayor,
everyone from Deng Xiaoping and down,
pretty much. He gave a lot of attention to these
visitors, in one case personally delivering a
cake to an official who turned 80 years old,
precisely at midnight. Trust me, not even in
the top ten weirdest things Jiang did during his
career. He got to meet and build a relationship
with basically everyone in Chinese politics, since
leaders during this time liked to escape Beijing
winters in Shanghai. He got to spend a lot of
time with Deng Xiaoping, since he had a habit of
visiting Shanghai every Chinese New Year.
The latter half of the ‘80s would be a fairly
trying time for the country, probably the biggest
period of danger the Communist Party ever faced.
Top leadership in the country was blindsided by
major student protests in Beijing in 1985, mainly
against corrupt officials. Hu Yaobang, general
secretary of the party at the time and one of the
major proponents of Deng Xiaoping’s reforms,
hastily put out a statement supporting the
protesters. Hu acknowledged and agreed with the
protesters’ concerns, mainly the need for younger
politicians and clamping down on corruption.
Deng also gave Hu limited approval to try some
of his envisioned political reforms.
This whole debacle led to some fairly nasty
top-level infighting in Beijing, which
Jiang wanted to avoid in Shanghai,
which was facing similar protests. Protests broke
out at most of Shanghai’s universities, including
Jiang’s former school. Jiang went to give a speech
in front of these protesters, which turned into
a three hour long shouting match, culminating in
Jiang reciting the Gettysburg Address, in English,
to the students. It was just a kind of confusing
ordeal, with neither side really understanding
what exactly happened, if anything.
He had a few private meetings with student
leaders, none of which led to anything. Jiang
refused to acquiesce to any of their demands,
and later deployed unarmed police to break
up the protests when they attempted to block
major roads. This backfired, and thousands
more were in the streets within a few days,
prompting Jiang to ask for help and advice from
Beijing. He was advised to meet with them again,
but this, yet again, went nowhere.
Factory workers also began joining the protests,
prompting much attention to be given to the
situation by Beijing. Incredibly luckily for
Jiang, the protests died out after a few days,
with no strong action needing to be taken. It’s
debated why this happened, but Jiang’s sympathy
towards student movements and his genuine desire
for reform, albeit more limited than the students’
demands, helped assuage their concerns.
In Beijing at the same time, top leaders were
making a decision that would totally never come
back to bite them. Deng Xiaoping and Zhao Ziyang
were in the process of removing Hu Yaobang from
power, for going too far with his political
reforms. These reforms had led to an easing of
tensions, and the dispersal of most protests.
Surely this will have no consequences.
Jiang had impressed top leaders with his
relatively middle-of-the-road approach,
not angering any particular group. Jiang made sure
to quickly fall in line with the new party line,
that being railing against the “bourgeois
liberalism” of Hu Yaobang. He reinforced
this general position with an interview with the
Los Angeles Times in 1987, where he argued that
putting down the protests was needed to allow for
Shanghai’s greater opening up to the world.
And open up, Shanghai sure did. Jiang got approval
to formally transition Shanghai to a market
economy, and did away with many regulations in the
city. He also hired many competent subordinates to
handle the day-to-day economics and management of
the city, so he could focus more on the government
and political side of things. This gave him
the opportunity to frequently meet with the
many foreign visitors to Shanghai, which was now
a common stop on foreign tours of China, and gave
him some positive attention internationally.
He also now had a free hand to talk about
some political reforms, though very minor and
vague, mainly giving speeches about how “taboo
opinions” should be allowed to be voiced.
The catalyst for national reforms, Hu Yaobang,
died in 1989. Jiang was actually in attendance at
the meeting where Hu had the first of a series of
heart attacks that would kill him in April of that
year. Hu Yaobang was the only major politician
talking about serious political reforms, and the
opening of intellectual spaces. Gatherings and
memorials for Hu quickly turned into protests in
Beijing, which became huge protests in Shanghai
when word spread there. Many people were
outraged by how he was removed from power
and the attempted censorship of his ideas.
The protests in Shanghai weren’t as big of a deal
as what a certain newspaper was printing, that
being the World Economic Herald. Considered the
most reformist media outlet in the country, they
were now openly publishing articles supporting
Hu and slamming top leaders for ousting him from
power. Jiang’s initial response was to demand the
paper vet all new articles with party censors
in Shanghai. The editor of the paper refused,
uncensored versions of the paper were printed,
and the editor was nowhere to be found.
The local party apparatus quickly made the paper
be subservient to a five-person review board,
and Jiang fired the editor. This, considering
what the response to these protests would
famously culminate in, seems relatively minor
and restrained. Zhao Ziyang, now the second most
important person in the country, didn’t think
so, and was furious. Zhao had a reputation as
a reformer, and the World Economic Herald
was one of his biggest sources of support,
now essentially decapitated. Zhao criticized
Jiang for his hasty decision, calling his
solution simplistic. Jiang also had pressure from
the hardliners in the party, since his review
board wasn’t doing their jobs, and were still
letting anti-government articles through.
This turned into a weeks-long battle, mostly Zhao
and Jiang sending angry letters to each other,
with Zhao on the attack and Jiang playing
defense. Things weren’t helped by Gorbachev’s
visit to China, in which Shanghai would be a stop.
Jiang was barely able to rally enough police to
clear Gorby’s route of the estimated 100,000
protesters now in Shanghai. A few days later,
Jiang was finally able to talk down most of
the protesters, walking into the crowd with a
megaphone, promising to hold talks and supporting
the anti-corruption side of their protest.
Back in Beijing, Zhao Ziyang tried a similar
tactic, walking into Tiananmen and basically
saying “we’re really sorry about all this, can
you all just go home?” When this didn’t work,
top leaders came back with a different plan:
martial law. Surely, this would never come
back to bite them. Soldiers tried to clear
Beijing of protesters over several days,
but were largely unsuccessful, and only served
to turn a few protesters to violence.
Zhao became the protesters’ newest target,
and there were calls for him to step down.
Deng Xiaoping’s patience with his continued
bungling of the protests was wearing thin,
and he began exploring options for a replacement
as general secretary. Deng convened a secret
meeting with a few top officials on May 27th,
where Jiang Zemin was selected to be the new
general secretary, after a few hours of debate.
The decision came down to his relative youth,
success with economic reforms, and being a fairly
personable guy who could help with the protests
and similar discontent in the future. Most
people were shocked and surprised by this choice,
as was Jiang, who had no idea he was
even up for consideration until a private
meeting with Deng a few days later.
He got acquainted with his new position for a
few days, and boy, what days those were. These
were the final days of the Beijing protests,
culminating in the Tiananmen Square Massacre.
Jiang’s role in the events of these days are
hard to say, we pretty much only have anecdotal
accounts. Some say he had no involvement, some
say he was deeply involved. What we do know is he
was generally against the heavy-handed response,
and pushed for police reform, preferring them to
use non-lethal means for crowd control.
Jiang was officially elected as
general secretary on June 28th, 1989,
around the same time Deng Xiaoping retired from
politics, formally turning over the keys. People
in China and internationally were surprised by
this selection, he was a periphery politician
at best, a liability at worst. Basically
nobody thought his term would last long,
one diplomat in Beijing said he would be running
a transitional government at best. Though,
many were hopeful. He was untainted by many of
the scandals and issues of Beijing politics,
and had shown his willingness to work with
foreign countries throughout his career.
Jiang immediately got to work on addressing a few
basic concerns of the protesters, mainly on the
corruption front. He tightened regulations
on government officials, no more banquets,
foreign cars, or big year-end bonuses. He also
handled the response to foreign media about the
Tiananmen incident, in a major press conference
where any question was permitted. He asserted that
the soldiers only opened fire after they had
been attacked by protesters. He stressed that
this was a one-off incident, and that it shouldn’t
dissuade foreign investment and interest in China.
Overall, foreign media was very
impressed with his demeanor,
a Chinese leader taking questions from the
press this openly was unheard of.
He spent the rest of 1989 and 1990 bolstering
domestic support, mainly making public visits
to various mines, factories and farms. He
visited Kim Il-Sung in North Korea, assuring
each other they would work together to fend off
the collapse of communism happening in Europe,
from spreading to Asia. Invited a few university
students to Zhongnanhai, that’s nice. All in all,
pretty typical stuff for a new leader to
do. He still didn’t really have a base,
and was very dependent on the support and advice
of Deng Xiaoping in these first years.
1992 saw one of Deng’s last major political moves,
his famous “Southern Tour.” Economic reforms had
been curtailed by conservative elements in
the government in the aftermath of Tiananmen,
and foreign investors were scared off from
China by the incident. Guangdong and Shenzhen
in the south were still progressing with the
reforms, and were the fastest growing regions
in China as a result. Deng visited these
areas, and praised them for their progress,
and spoke against those still against free
market reform. While Jiang wasn’t really a
focus of anything he said, Jiang still interpreted
many of his comments as criticizing him, and moved
more towards reform as a result.
1992 was mostly Jiang securing his position,
or more accurately, Deng securing it for
him. Deng got the military to fall in line,
and replaced many of the most conservative
politicians with younger reform-minded ones.
Deng made a twenty minute long speech in front of
the National People’s Congress supporting Jiang,
crushing any doubt of him as Deng’s formal
successor. Jiang made a couple international
trips, one to Japan and one to South Korea,
after finally establishing diplomatic relations
with the latter. This made Kim Il-Sung mad
and his request for military material aid
was rebuffed by Jiang that same year.
Funny anecdote from this time, Jiang really
liked to receive reports and talk directly
with those who reported to him. Dr. Song Jian,
a scientist and mathematician who
worked in China’s aerospace industry,
was requested to just… give him any articles
or papers he found interesting. He’d just walk
into Jiang’s office and hand him some scientific
documents every once in a while. Incredibly funny,
this is how I’d run a government.
By 1993, Jiang was very secure in his position,
and was fairly popular as a leader. He began
fulfilling some of his promises he made earlier,
like police reform. The People’s Armed Police,
which were essentially cops with military
gear before, were given proper riot control
equipment. He also transferred many units from
military authority to civilian police authority.
Don’t think he was some ACAB crusader, though.
He also expanded the powers of the Ministry
of State Security, China’s intelligence and
secret police agency. He allowed the MSS to spy
on basically anyone they wanted without a warrant,
and had them report directly to him.
Inflation and rising costs were a big problem
at this time. China’s economy was growing by
twelve percent each year, by far the highest
in the world. Costs however, were increasing by
about forty percent each year for most goods and
services. This was mainly curtailed by reducing
the amount of loans given out by the People’s
Bank of China, which slowed overall growth,
but prevented a huge inflation crisis.
1993 had quite a lot of diplomatic activity,
with some back channel talks between Jiang and
the president of Taiwan via the US ambassador
to China. He tried to get Beijing to host the
2000 Olympics, didn’t work. Placated Britain
about Hong Kong, who were suddenly freaking out
about there being a new leader in Beijing. Got
a container ship seized by the US for allegedly
carrying chemical weapons, though none were ever
found. I’m sure America will be careful about
making accusations like that in the future.
1994 was marked with continued austerity measures,
now increasingly unpopular. Some conservatives
in the government argued with Jiang that he
should enforce Mao-style price controls
to fix the immediate issue. While Jiang
was deeply bothered by the continuing inflation
problem, he trusted Deng, and knew allowing the
free market to continue, even if it had some
short term growing pains, would be beneficial
for the country overall.
He continued many of the military
reforms Deng started in the ‘80s, and made a ton
of visits to military academies and installations.
Overall, he had a fairly hands off approach to
the military, as the first leader of the People’s
Republic without any military experience.
China-US relations deteriorated quite a bit,
with Jiang and Clinton exchanging heated remarks
about each other’s governments. Clinton demanded
China improve their human rights situation,
and Jiang accused America of trying to make
China into a vassal. Things weren’t going well
with Britain either, as he tried to hastily
renegotiate the exact terms for the return of Hong
Kong to China, scheduled to happen in 1997, and
was very angry when the British rebuffed him. He
did formally get the ball rolling on joining the
World Trade Organization this year, too.
1995 saw greater economic policy centralization,
not to be confused with a return to a planned
economy. It was common at this time for the
government to draft a new policy, and receive
unanimous support from provincial governors,
but with various explanations about how
their particular province should be exempt.
He personally met with every provincial governor,
and made them pledge to follow Beijing’s policies,
whatever they may be, with threats
of dismissal if they refused.
He also began taking greater control of the
media, prohibiting foreign investment in
Chinese media organizations, and forbidding
Chinese reporters from writing for foreign
organizations. Media were also prohibited
from reporting on “negative phenomena,” such
as protests or legal disputes.
He gave a speech on Taiwan that would
set the tone for policy regarding that dispute
for a while. Jiang softened the tone on Taiwan
quite a bit, saying they would be allowed
to retain their own government, military,
and independent legal system in a hypothetical
reunification. This speech made nobody happy,
he threw in a vague military threat at the end,
which made Taiwan nervous. The military and rest
of the government wasn’t happy about Taiwan
being given all these concessions.
Dr. Song Jian, his scientist friend, also
formally made a proposal to the government
this year for a program to advance science
and education in the country. Jiang got this
proposal pushed through the Politburo, and
pledged to end China’s exam-based educational
system. Yeah, that really worked out.
China-US relations only got worse, when the
president of Taiwan visited America. Clinton had
allegedly promised Jiang at a meeting in Moscow
that the president wouldn’t be allowed in, but
the trip was approved anyway. Jiang felt betrayed,
and vocally condemned the US for this. Jiang
stated privately to military leaders that “the
Taiwan independence movement is getting out of
hand,” and to increase military readiness.
This would lead to the Third Taiwan Strait
Crisis, continuing into 1996. Tons of missile
tests and naval exercises surrounded the island
for months, leading to a fairly major economic
downturn for Taiwan. Shipping costs exploded and
the stock market crashed. It eventually died down,
with China generally considered to have “won”
the incident, coming out looking stronger than
they entered. Though, it did allow that
Taiwanese president to win a comfortable
election victory during the crisis.
He made a visit to the UN General Assembly,
making a speech speaking against “big powers”
who use the pretext of “human rights” to
interfere with other countries. He met with
Clinton on the sidelines, and the two of them
talked for a bit and largely made up.
1996 saw some interesting messaging from Jiang.
He gave speeches telling officials to “focus
on politics” and “increase cultural and moral
fortitude.” Jiang spoke about how China’s
cultural, spiritual, and moral aspects
were falling behind its economic and material
development. This was a strange turn to say the
least, and worried many people. Talk like this was
last heard during the Cultural Revolution.
The ideas he put forth, what would be
known as “Jiang Thought,” encompassed a
broad integration of the new free market
thinking and system with the old Marxist
ideas of the country. More broadly, it was
pushing back against Western culture that was
increasingly intruding into China. This was just
against the cultural side of Western influence,
Western money and expertise was still more than
welcome. An article in the People’s Daily put
it as “China shouldn’t give up eating for
fear of choking.” Ultimately, this wasn’t
turned into concrete policy, and was just a vague
directive to improve morality and thinking.
He visited a ton of countries in 1996, mainly
in Africa, Central Asia, and Europe. Perhaps
the most famous images from these trips were
him very obviously combing his hair in front of
the king of Spain. He did a brief tour around
Asia, became the first modern Chinese leader
to visit India and sang Elvis Presley songs
with the president of the Philippines.
The two most important events of 1997
had be to the death of Deng Xiaoping,
and the return of Hong Kong to China. Deng
Xiaoping’s death was pretty inconsequential,
his health had been declining for a few years,
and everything was prepared well in advance.
Jiang gave a fifty minute long speech at
his funeral, and took the opportunity to
reinforce his political position. Recordings
of Deng praising Jiang were rebroadcast on TV,
a soundbite of Deng saying “the choice of Jiang
Zemin is correct” was frequently repeated.
For Hong Kong, the handover was also very
smooth and rehearsed, but not without some
minor controversies. The head of the Hong Kong
government, the position of governor, would be
replaced by the position of Chief Executive.
The first Chief Executive, Tung Chee-hwa,
had been chosen by a 400 person committee, rather
than a direct election in Hong Kong as many were
expecting. Prime Minister Tony Blair boycotted
the handover ceremony as a result.
1997 also saw Jiang’s first formal summit with the
United States. This was a very extensive visit,
going all over the country. Protests by
various activist groups, human rights,
Tibetan, and Taiwanese especially, were planning
gatherings at every stop along the way.
The trip was overall a success, with Jiang
and Clinton making firm progress on a variety
of issues. The two finally got along at a more
personal level, with Jiang referring to Clinton
as “my friend Bill Clinton” from now on. He took
a few news interviews, and answered plenty of
unscripted questions at press conferences.
1998 was a fairly eventful year, some of the
most notable events were an increase in
foreign movies being allowed into China,
after the success of Titanic, a visit from
Bill Clinton, and the elevation of Hu Jintao,
who would succeed Jiang as leader eventually.
India and Pakistan exchanged nuclear tests,
increasing tension for a while in Asia. One of
India’s cited reasons for their test was the
threat posed by China, which Jiang was apparently
legitimately surprised and confused by.
Some interesting military reforms happened
this year, regarding the military’s influence
in business. Due to budget cuts in the
‘80s, some parts of the military became
involved both legitimate and illegitimate
business, with surprisingly far reach. The
PLA was operating everything from hotels
to nightclubs to airlines to cell networks
to professional basketball teams. They also
participated in smuggling and bootlegging,
particularly movies and software.
Jiang had quite a bit of sway with the military
now, and decreed that all such enterprises should
be immediately broken up and dissolved. Top brass
complied, but there were many grumblings from
less senior officers. He further stretched
his political capital with the military when
he required their assistance in dealing with
major flooding in the country, that displaced
more than a quarter billion people.
Things were generally fine with both of these,
though there were some minor protests in 1999
by workers who lost their jobs when their PLA
employers had to shutter their businesses. These
were hardly the protests of concern, however. On
April 25th, over 10,000 members of a cult known as
Falun Gong began encircling Zhongnanhai. With an
estimated two million members, not much in terms
of China’s vast population, many top leaders had
never even heard of the people surrounding the
main government building in Beijing. This
protest was over some Falun Gong members
who had been arrested for protesting in front
of a newspaper office that printed an article
they believed was defamatory to their sect.
The protest was dispersed fairly easily, after a
spokesman was sent out to speak with them. He said
the government had no dispute with them, but that
they couldn’t engage in this type of behavior. The
protesters very quickly left after this.
Jiang was enraged by this incident. It had
come completely out of nowhere, and worse yet,
it was revealed there were party members among
the protesters. Jiang also had a more personal
grievance with the cult. A friend of his had
joined for the meditation and exercise part of
their beliefs, but died from a brain hemorrhage
after she refused medical care due to the cult’s
prohibition against modern medicine.
His response to Falun Gong would have to wait,
as a much more important event in May captured
national attention: the NATO bombing of the
Chinese embassy in Serbia. This was during the
broader NATO air campaign against Serbia, where an
American B-2 Spirit dropped bombs on the Chinese
embassy, killing three people and injuring dozens
more. The incident is still pretty confusing, to
say the least. The CIA, who organized the attack,
claimed it was a mere mistake, which seems hard
to believe, given the precision bombs used. On
the other hand, there’s not really a benefit
to attacking a random Chinese embassy.
Jiang did get a lick in on Falun Gong with
it, joking that “if Falun Gong masters can
predict the future, why couldn’t they predict
the attack on our embassy?” Huge anti-American
protests broke out around China, snarling
many of Jiang’s reforms. His opening up to
the West now seemed much less appealing
to many people, and his bid to join the
World Trade Organization was put on hold.
Rocks were thrown at the US embassy in Beijing,
and consulates were surrounded. Very strong
statements against America and NATO were
put out by various government organs. The
protests wore on for about a week, before
the government finally intervened to halt them.
Jiang finally accepted a phone call from Clinton,
after declining them for the entire week.
Attention of the government quickly turned back to
Falun Gong, who had restrictions placed on them,
and in practice it was a total ban. It was now
illegal to have gatherings, spread cult materials,
or to demonstrate for the cult. An arrest warrant
was also put out for Li Hongzhi, the leader of the
cult, who had left the country prior. Falun Gong’s
response was to claim they had been responsible
for the NATO bombing of the Chinese embassy, using
their leader’s supposed supernatural abilities.
I’m not kidding. But, for now, the ban elicited
some critical comments about the government,
but it didn’t have too many consequences.
2000 had some big policy changes, including
the implementation of Jiang Zemin’s “Three
Represents” theory. This was essentially
a plan to “modernize Marxism.” The three
things to “represent” with this policy are
advanced productive forces, advanced culture,
and the interests of the Chinese people. This
whole thing sounds kind of strange in English,
I mean, even the name sounds like something from
a bad sci-fi book, but it makes more sense in
Chinese. The long and short of it was an attempt
to update China’s Marxist rhetoric and culture
to incorporate the new economic realities
and wealth now sweeping the nation.
He focused again on education reform in
2000, setting a goal of China being one
of the top ten countries in science by
2010. Jiang even got to write a couple
pieces for the journal Science, an honor not
usually afforded to national leaders.
2000 saw two of his most famous moments
on camera, the first being an interview
with Mike Wallace of 60 Minutes. It’s quite the
interview, it’s on YouTube if you want to watch
it. Wallace didn’t hold back with his questions,
and Jiang fired back with some tough questions of
his own. The interview left many in America with
a good impression of Jiang, even if the editing
and translation choices for some of his comments
were a little inaccurate, to say the least.
The other media incident happened a few weeks
later, at a press conference in Beijing. Jiang
blew up at some reporters from Hong Kong after
one asked if his endorsement of Tung Chee-hwa’s
reelection campaign was an “imperial appointment.”
The result was… I’ll just let you watch for
yourself. If you’ve seen any video of Jiang Zemin,
this is probably the clip you’ve seen.
Absolutely amazing.
Ultimately, these two events
didn’t really matter much, but Jiang got a couple
vague criticisms from Politburo members about how
politicians should “show decorum.”
2001 was a low point in US-China relations,
with a change in leadership in America, and
the Hainan Island incident. The US flew,
and still flies, reconnaissance flights in
international waters, but near the Chinese coast,
quite frequently. China typically responds with
fighters to intercept the plane, keeping a safe
distance. It’s this weird sort of diplomatic
dance, but it’s a pretty common phenomenon.
On April 1st, 2001, a US Navy EP-3 signal
intelligence plane was conducting one of
these patrols near the island of Hainan. Two
Chinese J-8 fighters were sent to intercept
and monitor the American aircraft. It still
isn’t clear what exactly happened, but one
of the fighters and the American plane collided
with each other, crashing the fighter into the
sea and the death of its pilot, and forcing
the American plane to land on Hainan.
The new American president, George W. Bush,
demanded China not tamper with or board the
downed plane, claiming it had sovereign immunity.
That worked about as well as those sovereign
citizen license plates. Jiang blamed the US for
the incident, and demanded an official apology.
He also ordered a huge search and rescue operation
for the downed pilot, to no avail, sadly.
The US was reluctant to issue an apology,
seeing their plane as having done nothing
more than make an emergency landing. China
allowed American diplomats to visit the crew
of the plane, confirming their wellbeing.
The crew was held in China for ten days,
when they were freed by an official apology
from the State Department for the incident. The
plane was eventually returned to the US as well,
though after it had been completely disassembled
and analyzed by Chinese engineers.
In happier news, Beijing won its bid to
host the 2008 Olympics in July of that
year. In good news for people who like
cheap products but bad news for anyone outside of
China with a manufacturing job, China also joined
the World Trade Organization that year.
Jiang and Bush didn’t get along for the first
few months of his term, but they reconciled after
Jiang supported America after 9/11. They held a
summit in Shanghai, where Jiang firmly threw
China’s support behind the US anti-terrorism
effort. This was partially to get a free hand to
combat terrorism within China, particularly in
Xinjiang, where Chinese anti-terror efforts had
been criticized as heavy-handed before.
Jiang’s time as leader was coming to an end,
and it was time to elevate a successor. He chose
a rather obscure politician, Hu Jintao.
Hu was the governor of Tibet for a time,
and was generally considered a fairly
middle of the road, reliable, technocrat,
sort of like Jiang. He was a pretty low-profile,
respected, safe choice. There were actually many
who wanted Jiang to remain as leader, beyond his
allocated term, particularly from the military,
surprisingly. Jiang rejected these requests,
stating how he thought it was important
for China to have a younger leader.
2002, the last full year of Jiang’s leadership,
was pretty uneventful. Mainly his time was spent
dealing with the boring internal politics of the
change in leaders, with a few minor international
trips. He got some of his ideas, most notably the
“Three Represents” written into the constitution.
He stayed on as chairman of the Central Military
Commission until 2004, but his leadership
was de facto over at the end of 2002.
It was all rather unceremonious and
abrupt, mostly done behind the scenes,
as is typical in Chinese history. Though, Jiang’s
political career was not over, even in retirement.
He kept a modicum of influence through a group of
of politicians generally known as the “Shanghai
clique” or “Shanghai gang.” I don’t want to get
too into the weeds on this, trying to guess at the
inner workings of the Politburo in the last 30
years is basically impossible. You’re better
off consulting a magic eight ball than some of
these articles written about it, I swear.
The TL; DR is the Shanghai gang was a bunch of
Jiang’s friends who stayed on after he retired,
some notable members being Zhou Yongkang
and Wang Huning. They had some minor clashes
with Hu Jintao, and the gang was generally
broken up under Xi Jinping. What precisely
they did and affected is anyone’s guess.
Jiang kept a fairly low profile in retirement,
appearing occasionally at events and on
holidays, mainly. But, he kept a very high
profile in the minds of many Chinese people,
through the greatest internet meme of all:
toad culture. You can’t talk about Jiang Zemin
without at least mentioning toad culture.
Started as a joke about Jiang’s demeanor and his
somewhat toad-like appearance, it has morphed
into a strange sort of counterculture. Hu
Jintao’s and Xi Jinping’s terms both saw severe
curtailments of personal liberties and rights
in China, creating a longing for the much more
hands-off era of Jiang Zemin.
There’s a ton of specific memes and
jokes as a part of toad culture. Some of my
favorites are repeating some of Jiang’s more
ridiculous quotes, like “too simple, sometimes
naive.” “True fans will always recognize him”
is another good one, regarding images of
things that have a vague resemblance to
Jiang. Some other miscellaneous memes include
referring to him as “the elder,” or “plus one
second,” wishing a long life to Jiang.
But, as we all as must learn, internet points
don’t matter much in real life, and Jiang
Zemin passed away on November 30th, 2022,
at the age of 96. He was just a kid. Jiang Zemin
was quite the guy, both as a person and as a
leader. He oversaw China’s meteoric rise in both
economic terms, but also in scientific, cultural,
and military terms. While certainly not without
controversy and scandal, he is remembered as a
steady hand, and as a personable guy.
He navigated crisis and instability,
and integrated Western-style capitalism with
Chinese-style Marxism. His moderation and wisdom
saw China through a period that could have
been incredibly destabilizing and dangerous.
He’s remembered for the relative openness
and freedom of his time, when the Chinese
political sphere was full of hope and progress,
rather than the tensions of the modern era.